Okay בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's דף daf is כ"ו, chaf vav,
דף daf of the מסכת, masechet, ha, of the פרק. perek. And
we pick up at the bottom of כ"ה עמוד ב' chaf hey
amud bet and we are with מעשה שחלצו. ma'aseh she'chalatzu. So we're
finishing the opinion in the משנה mishna that you don't need a
בית דין, beis din, that it said that maybe only two or
even fewer is good. רבי שמעון בן יוחנן הסנדלר, Rabbi Shimon ben
Yochanan HaSandlar, we say we don't rule that way, בדיעבד bedi'eved you
do need a בית דין. beis din. We also said לכתחילה lechatchila
three is enough, but then there's a story that מעשה באחד שחלץ
בינו לבינה, ma'aseh b'echad she'chalatz beino l'veinah, a man did חליצה chalitza
between him and her privately in בית האסורים beis ha'asurim ובא מעשה
לפני רבי עקיבא והכשיר. u'ba ma'aseh lifnei Rabbi Akiva v'hichshir. רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva said it was כשר. kosher. So רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
is now the seemingly author of this position that בדיעבד bedi'eved you
don't need a בית דין. beis din. So let's see what the
גמרא Gemara says.
מעשה שחלץ ma'aseh she'chalatz five lines from the bottom on כ"ה עמוד
ב'. chaf hey amud bet. So the גמרא Gemara says בינו לבינה
מי ידעינן? beino l'veinah mi yadana? How do we know it was
between them? Meaning okay, they're reporting it, but how can we פסקן?
pasken? Like maybe as far as God is concerned she's a חלוצה,
chaluza, but how can we as a בית דין beis din rule
that way? Like it's just what evidence do we have? So the
גמרא Gemara says אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל בעדים ראוהו שצופין מבחוץ.
amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel b'eidim ra'uhu she-samim mibachutz. No, there were
עדים eidim that saw it from the outside and they were enough
to provide evidence that the event had occurred, but not a, they
weren't a בית דין. beis din. And number two, this gets into
a whole question of when you need עדים eidim not just as
proof that something occurred but to actually effectuate it, make it considered
legally binding. Like for example by a קידושין, kiddushin, even if you
have a hundred percent knowledge that it occurred, if there were not
עדים, eidim, it was not, it's not legally binding. That's called עדי
קיום eidei kiyum as opposed to עדי בירור eidei birur which are
just to clarify, to bring evidence. So it could be that for
the need of עדי קיום eidei kiyum you need them, you need
not just them to have seen it, but you need the people
participants to be aware that the עדים eidim were there, you need
them to be more physically present. So here he's saying we have
enough that suffices as evidence that it occurred, but they're certainly, because
people were looking at it from the outside, but they were certainly
not a בית דין beis din and might not even have been
עדים eidim that were effectuating the
חליצה. chalitza. In principle it was done completely privately even though there's
sufficient evidence, even though we do know as a matter of fact
that it did occur. עדים ראוהו שצופין מבחוץ. eidim ra'uhu she-tzofin mibachutz.
איבעיא להו, iba'ya lehu, now there is the question. מעשה שחלץ בינו
לבינה אבראי, ma'aseh she'chalatz beino l'veinah a'varai,
did the story of this חליצה, chalitza, this private חליצה chalitza happen
outside, out of prison? ובא מעשה לפני רבי עקיבא בבית האסורים, u'ba
ma'aseh lifnei Rabbi Akiva b'veis ha'asurim, and רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva though
was informed about it in prison because רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva was
imprisoned by the Romans before he was martyred. או דילמא, o dilma,
or do we say מעשה שחלץ בינו לבינה בבית האסורים? ma'aseh she'chalatz
beino l'veinah b'veis ha'asurim? The event, the event happened in prison and
the story came to רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva wasn't in prison. So who was in prison? The participants or
רבי עקיבא? Rabbi Akiva? So אמר רב יהודה אמר רב בבית האסורים
היה מעשה ולבית האסורים בא מעשה. amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav, b'veis
ha'asurim haya ma'aseh u'l'veis ha'asurim ba ma'aseh. It happened in prison and
it came to רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva in prison. Now תוספות Tosfos
points out that in the משנה mishna it's a bizarre question because
the משנה mishna is very clear that the story happened in prison.
The language of the משנה mishna is the language of the משנה
mishna was מעשה באחד שחלץ בינו לבינה בבית האסורים ma'aseh b'echad she'chalatz
beino l'veinah b'veis ha'asurim ובא מעשה לפני רבי עקיבא u'ba ma'aseh lifnei
Rabbi Akiva
והכשיר. v'hichshir.
So clearly the event was in prison and then it was reported
to רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. So תוספות Tosfos says if you don't
have the ו vav of ובא מעשה, u'ba ma'aseh, you have מעשה
שחלץ בינו לבינה בבית האסורים ma'aseh she'chalatz beino l'veinah b'veis ha'asurim בא
מעשה לפני רבי עקיבא והכשיר, ba ma'aseh lifnei Rabbi Akiva v'hichshir,
then it would be possible to read it מעשה שחלץ בינו לבינה
ma'aseh she'chalatz beino l'veinah בבית האסורים בא מעשה לפני רבי עקיבא. b'veis
ha'asurim ba ma'aseh lifnei Rabbi Akiva.
So if you drop the ו vav it's maybe possible to read
it that way, but it's still a stretch. And תוספות Tosfos says
the reason, and certainly why would you read it both ways? It
happened in prison, brought to רבי עקיבא? Rabbi Akiva? So תוספות Tosfos
says if you look at the ירושלמי Yerushalmi you see that there
was a tradition not only that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva had been
imprisoned by the Romans, but there's a tradition that this story had
been brought to him in prison and therefore trying to read that
into the משנה mishna as well. And he brings out a fascinating
story about how they communicated with him in prison to ask this
question. So if you look at the three lines from the bottom
of the bottom of the page of the last תוספות, Tosfos, he
says like this to
the end of the like third line from the bottom ויש לומר
דידוע הגמרא v'yesh lomar d'yadu'a ha-Gemara שבא לפניו בבית האסורים. she-ba lefanav
b'veis ha'asurim. That
they knew it, that it happened to him in prison, so we
want to read that into the משנה. mishna. כדאמר בירושלמי, Kid'amar b'Yerushalmi,
and
here's the story in ירושלמי. Yerushalmi. יוחנן הסנדלר, Yochanan HaSandlar,
and remember the person in the משנה mishna before רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva that was quoted to say that you don't need a חליצה
chalitza in front of a בית דין beis din was רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon and יוחנן הסנדלר, Yochanan HaSandlar, they were the two in
the משנה mishna that said that you don't need a בית דין.
beis din. So here's the way the ירושלמי Yerushalmi has a story
that the same יוחנן הסנדלר Yochanan HaSandlar עבר קומי חבושין דרבי עקיבא.
avar kumi chavushin d'Rabbi Akiva. He passed... by the prison of רבי
עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. היה מכריז ואמר haya machriz v'amar
and he was like announcing and saying מן בעי מחטין מן בעי
צינון, man baei nach'tin man baei tzinon, who needs needles, who needs
pins like he was you know he was posing as a salesman
so he could get a secret message to רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva.
Okay, it wasn't they weren't smuggling like a file in a cake.
They were smuggling in halachic שאלות. shailos. Okay,
yeah, exactly although he was selling pins and needles and then he
sort of in the middle of who needs pins, who needs needles
he said מן בעי מחטין מן בעי צינון חליצה בינו לבינה מהו?
man baei nach'tin man baei tzinon chalitzah beno uveinam mahu?
Who knows what happened if the חליצה chalitzah was in private? Who
needs pins? Who needs needles? So מהו. mahu. So רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva אדיק מן כוותיה. adik min kavassei. So רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
stuck his head out of like out of the prison window like
between the bars, okay, and אמר ליה amar leh and he said
to him איכא כושין איכא כושת, iflach kushin iflach kashet, you have
כושין kushin which I think are I don't know some types of
like a pincushion I'm not sure exactly what כושין kushin are anyway
like a some type of a כוש kush is like I don't
know like a whatever anyway and then in the middle of saying
do you have כושין kushin which sounds like כשר kasher he sort
of he he snuck in the word it's כשר, kasher, it's כשר.
kasher. So okay so that's how they had their secret communication in
prison. All right anyway by the way so but we so that's
the story with רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva but we פוסקן pasken you
need three בדיעבד b'diavad and three even suffices לכתחילה l'chatchila and if
you take a look at the תוספות Tosafot before that רבי יוחנן
הסנדלר מכשיר בשנים Rabbi Yochanan Hasandlar machshir b'shnayim
I'm sorry the two before that לכתחילה בעי חמישה l'chatchila ba'i chamisha
I would have thought you needed five לכתחילה l'chatchila and the גמרא
Gemara said yesterday no you only need three so the תוספות Tosafot
says מכאן יש לומר דאין צריך חמישה אפילו לכתחילה mikan yesh lomar
de'ein tzarich chamisha afilu l'chatchila that even לכתחילה l'chatchila you don't need
five even לכתחילה l'chatchila three is the right number but and בדיעבד
b'diavad you need three ומיהו לפרסומי מילתא עבדינן בחמישה umihu l'farsumei milsa
avdinan l'chamisha even though you don't need even though לכתחילה l'chatchila you
don't to make it better we do five anyway because remember going
back to that whole גמרא Gemara about you know publicizing it more.
Okay top of כו עמוד א chaf vav amud aleph תנו רבנן
tanu rabanan rabbis taught חליצה מוטעת כשרה chalitza mutat keshera
a tricked חליצה chalitzah or a deceived חליצה chalitzah is כשר kasher
איזו היא חליצה מוטעת eizu hi chalitza mutat what is a deceived
חליצה chalitzah אמר ריש לקיש amar Reish Lakish כל שאומרים לו חלוץ
ובכך אתה
קונסה kol she'omrim lo chalot uv'kach ata konesah there's a man who
basically for some reason wanted to do יבום yibbum and he was
like you know it was improper either because they thought he wasn't
doing it לשם שמים l'shem shamayim or he was just interested in
his money whatever the case was or money excuse me so so
they basically wanted to persuade him to do חליצה chalitzah but nowadays
you could have a case where the guy just or whatever let's
move on later okay so therefore he wanted to do he wanted
to do יבום yibbum but they were trying to get him to
do חליצה chalitzah so what they said to him was hey buddy
look go through this חליצה chalitzah ceremony and then she'll be your
wife that's how we do יבום yibbum these days okay is we
do a חליצה chalitzah ceremony so which is fine you know plenty
of people are not knowledgeable about the specifics okay the question is
presumably this would be a perfect time where they might want to
drop the reciting of the verses which make it a little bit
explicit what the whole thing is about right לא חפצתי לקחתה lo
chafatzti lekachtah etc and we learned that בדיעבד b'diavad if you don't
do the reciting of the verses it's okay so therefore that would
be a deceived חליצה chalitzah which would be כשר kasher so אמר
רבי יוחנן amar Rabbi Yochanan so רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said back
to the to ריש לקיש Reish Lakish אני שונה ani shoneh I
teach בין שנתכוון הוא ולא נתכוונה היא בין שנתכוונה היא ולא נתכוון
הוא bein shemitkaven hu v'lo mitkavnah hi bein shemitkavnah hi v'lo mitkaven
hu אם שנתכוון נפשיה או שנתכוונה נפשיך im shemitkaven naksheih or shemitkavnah
naksheich חליצתה פסולה chalitzatah pesula it's invalid עד שיתכוונו שניהם ad sheyitkavnu
shneihem both of them have to intend for it to be an
effective חליצה chalitzah so
ואת
אמרת v'at amarta and you are saying חליצתה כשרה chalitzatah keshera that
if you think it affects יבום yibbum that it's כשר kasher now
maybe you could say you intend to do חליצה chalitzah not some
other act not like the גמרא Gemara said before just helping somebody
remove their shoe but he's saying it's not just כוונה kavana to
do an act of חליצה chalitzah but it's understanding what the act
is going to effectuate so how could you say it's כשר kasher
if you think it's going to effectuate its opposite יבום yibbum so
that's not חליצה מוטעת chalitza mutat that's totally פסול. pasul. So אלא
ella here's a חליצה מוטעת chalitza mutat that's כשר kasher כל שאומרים
לו חלוץ לה על מנת שתיתן לך מאתיים זוז kol she'omrim lo
chalot lamant shetitayn lach matayim zuz they bribe him and they say
agree to do חליצה chalitzah with her and and she'll give you
a two hundred זוז zuz but then they're not plan she's not
planning on giving it and she doesn't give it in the end
and nevertheless even though he was tricked right that might be a
better word than deceived tricked it's still כשר kasher because still he
had the intent that it should be a חליצה chalitzah and it
should be effective okay תניא נמי הכי tanya nami hachi we
taught similarly חליצה מוטעת כשרה chalitza mutat keshera a tricked חליצה chalitzah
is כשר kasher איזו היא חליצה מוטעת eizu hi chalitza mutat כל
שאומרים לו חלוץ לה kol she'omrim lo lachlotlah do a חליצה chalitzah
to her על מנת שתיתן לך מאתיים זוז al m'nat shetitayn lach
matayim zuz she'll give you 200 זוז zuz מעשה באשה אחת שנפלה
לפני יבם ma'aseh b'isha achas shenafelah lifnei yabam and
there was a story with a certain woman who fell before a
brother-in-law שאינה הגונה לו she'eina haguna lo was not fitting for her
for whatever reason as we'll see in a minute ואמרו לו v'amru
lo and they said to him חלוץ לה על מנת שתיתן לך
מאתיים זוז chalot lah al m'nat shetitayn lach matayim zuz do חליצה
chalitzah and she'll give you 200 זוז zuz ובא מעשה לפני רבי
עקיבא uva ma'aseh lifnei Rabbi Akiva the story came to רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva והכשירה vehichshirah and he said it was כשר kasher even
though she didn't give the 200 זוז zuz even though she never
planned on giving the 200 זוז zuz now the question is Okay,
you understand why you might want to trick somebody into it in
order to do the right thing. Of course, if Aunt רבקה Rivka
was here עליה השלום, aleha hashalom, you know she would obviously point
out that already in the גמרא, Gemara, you're getting the idea of
basically, I mean, you know, it's not a big move from bribing
a guy and tricking the guy to setting a precedent for extortion
and having the guy go ahead and then use this as a
tool for extorting money, although which obviously very sadly happens so often
in cases of גיטין Gittin today. But here at least, you know,
they were not going to, they were going to make the promise
and not follow it through. Of course, you... I don't know how
you hope that you get away with that trick more than a
few times before people start finding out, which is another question. But
the הלכה halacha question becomes, I don't understand, if they said על
מנת al menat and they made it conditional, how could it not
work, how could it work without satisfying the condition? So here רשי
Rashi quotes the famous statement in the... in... in גמרא בגיטין Gemara
in Gittin that says that, excuse me, in the גמרא בכתובות, Gemara
in Ketubot, that any condition, any act that cannot be given over
to a שליח shaliach cannot be made... cannot be made conditional. So
what does that mean? It means I can have you appoint you
as my agent to buy something for me. And therefore I can
also make a sale or a purchase on condition. I can appoint
you as my agent to give a גט get to my wife
or to receive, or the woman to make a man an agent,
a man or a woman, to receive a גט get from her
husband. Therefore, since agency is possible, stipulations and conditions are possible. But
you cannot have somebody be an agent to do יבום, yibbum, for
example, and you can't have somebody as an agent to do חליצה.
chalitza. Only the parties themselves. And therefore conditions are also not binding.
Now, what's the logic behind that?
Is there a שליח ליבום? shaliach l'yibbum?
I was teasing, but obviously you can't do that. So but you
also, right, but you also can't do it for... for חליצה. chalitza.
So what is the logic, why should stipulations be tied to agency?
And the logic is, and this is an important point that I
haven't mentioned until now, but a very famous רב חיים Rav Chaim
about חליצה. chalitza. He also asks, why is it possible that a
minor woman, we learned yesterday, there's a serious opinion that she might
be כשר kasher to do חליצה? chalitza? Right, normally, biblically, an act
can't be done by a minor, like a legally binding act like
a... a sale or a transaction or whatever. Why could חליצה? chalitza?
So what רב חיים Rav Chaim says is, just to answer the
חליצה chalitza point, is that it's not like the תורה Torah invests
you with the power to effect a status change or to, you
know, to do this. And then, you know, so I'm empowered to...
to...
like the same way I have a power, you know,
to transfer the ownership to be... of an object or to take
possession of an object, you know, and therefore it's... it's I'm the
one who's doing it, right? I as an agent, you know, as
an adult agent, whatever, in a legal system have the power to
do those things. It's not like you have the power to, you
know, to the man or the woman doing חליצה chalitza to sever
this relationship. The תורה Torah is not saying that. What the תורה
Torah saying is, if you go through the ritual, the תורה Torah
will sever the relationship. Or similarly by יבום. yibbum. If you go
and have sex, right, why is יבום yibbum even if it's an
accidental act of sex, we learned before, why is it effective, right?
When do you ever have that... oh, I accidentally, if I accidentally
purchase something of yours, I don't own it. I need to do
it with דעת. daat. But that's not true by יבום. yibbum. So
what רב חיים Rav Chaim says is because here, what the תורה
Torah saying is, if you go through the act and have sex,
or you go through the act and have חליצה, chalitza, the תורה
Torah is the one that either creates the bond or severs the
bond. It's not your effecting that change. It's you're just going through
the motions and the תורה Torah therefore, oh, you did this thing,
now the תורה Torah creates that change of status. You're not the
one empowered to create that change. So therefore, that's the logic why
also you can't make it... you can't... that's a, why you can't
have an agent do it. If I'm given power to take possession
of an object or to give over the possession of my object,
to marry a woman, to divorce a woman, I can transfer that
power to an agent. That's how agency is possible. But if it's
not that I'm given power, it's just I go through the motions
and the תורה Torah makes the change, so then I can't create
agency. I have to be the one going through the ritual. So
therefore, and that's the same reason why I can't stipulate. Because I,
in the end, am not the one that determines whether this effect
will take place or not. The תורה Torah does it when certain
conditions were met. So since the תורה Torah is the one doing
it, therefore I'm not in the position to stipulate whether and under
what conditions will it or won't it take effect. So that's the
logic why, if it's not given over to a שליח, shaliach, that
means it's not something that you're invested with the power. If you
were invested with the power, you could transfer that power. But since
you can't transfer that power, clearly you're not invested, clearly it's the
תורה Torah or the legal system that is doing it once you
do particular things. And therefore you're not empowered also to make stipulations.
So that's a very important idea that we never fully fleshed out
with יבום yibbum and חליצה. chalitza. That's why the possibility that even
a minor could do חליצה. chalitza. Why the idea that יבום Yibum
doesn't necessarily require to be done with דעת, Daas, and here why
the גמרא Gemara is saying that you don't have to satisfy the
condition. So you're allowed to deceive somebody, promise them money, and then
go ahead and the thing will they in the end of the
day intended to do the act of חליצה, Chalitza, it'll take effect,
and you don't need and then it'll be effect even if the
money isn't paid out, because the חליצה Chalitza was not the condition
was not binding. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues. ההוא דאתא
לקמיה דרבי חייא, Hahu de'asa lekamei de'Rabbi Chiya, a certain person came
in front of רבי חייא בר אבא. Rabbi Chiya bar Abba. אמר
ליה, Amar lei, he said to her, בתי עמדי, Bitti amidi, my
daughter stand up, meaning and meaning he was basically telling her time
to you know, this man wants you to go home with you
and do יבום, Yibum, take you as his wife, get up, you
know, go with him, do יבום. Yibum.
So not in front of the court hopefully, but anyway. אמרה ליה,
Amra lei, so she said to him, אימא ישיבתו זו היא עמידתו.
Eima yeshivato zo hi amidato. I will say in this case, my
sitting in my place is tantamount to standing, meaning I think I'm
better off not going with him, was a sort of way of
saying it. Some have the גרסא Girsa אמר לה אימא, Amar lah
eima, her mother said this to him, but anyway let's have she
said it to him. Okay, actually I'm better off sitting here, not
going with him. אמר לה, Amar lah, so he said to her,
ידעת ליה, Yadata lei, do you know him? Is like something up
with this guy, your this brother-in-law? אמרה ליה, Amra lei, אין, In,
yes. ממונו הוא דחזא לה, Mamono hu dechaza lah, he sees that
I've got money, or it's the mother speaking, he sees that she's
got money, ובעי למיכליה מינה, Uvai lemichlei minah, and he wants to
consume it from her. Basically he's only interested in her in the
money, he's going to do יבום, Yibum, take her money, and then
divorce her. אמר לה, Amar lah, so he said to her, לא
ניחא לך? Lo nicha lach? Are you do you not want to
do יבום? Yibum? אמרה ליה, Amra lei,
לא, Lo, no, I don't want to do יבום. Yibum. אמר ליה,
Amar lei, so he said to the man, חלוץ לה בתחת הקונסא.
Chalotz lah betachat hakonsa. The first case of tricking that we saw,
which רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said was not good, do חליצה Chalitza
and that'll make you married to her. לבתר דחלץ לה, Lebasar dechalatz
lah, now, we said what do you mean, we just said that's
not going to work. Ah, but he had another trick up his
sleeve. לבתר דחלץ לה, Lebasar dechalatz lah, excuse me,
after he did חליצה Chalitza with her, אמר ליה, Amar lei, he
said to him, אה השתא מיהא איפסלה לה. Ah, hashta miha ifsela
lah. You know what, the חליצה Chalitza didn't work because A, it
doesn't make you married to her, and B, it's true it didn't
work to make you separated from her, but what it was effective
of was it was a חליצה פסולה. Chalitza pesula. You remember what
the הלכה Halacha is about a חליצה פסולה? Chalitza pesula? After a
חליצה פסולה Chalitza pesula you're not allowed to do יבום. Yibum. So
ha, okay, it didn't work. It didn't make you married, it also
didn't make you חלוצה, Chaluza, but it prevents now you're not able
to do יבום. Yibum. Since you're now anyway not able to do
יבום, Yibum, השתא מיהא איפסלה לה, Hashta miha ifsela lah, חלוץ לה
חליצה מעלייתא, Chalotz lah Chalitza ma'alyasa,
might as well go ahead and do a good חליצה Chalitza with
her כי היכי דתשתרי לעלמא Ki heichi detishari le'alma in order to
free her. Okay, so he fooled he tricked him in a situation
where now יבום Yibum was not possible, so now he had to
do חליצה. Chalitza. Of course that's a tricky situation to be in,
because then the man out of spite might refuse to do the
good חליצה. Chalitza. What? You tricked me and now I can't do
יבום? Yibum? I'm refusing to do חליצה. Chalitza. So that's a question
if that's really going to work. So now the better trick is
to promise him money and not pay it up, which is now
what we're going to see in the next story, yes.
Is this רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya the תנא? Tanna?
I don't think so, it's a רבי חייא בר Rabbi Chiya bar
what was it?
בר אבא.
Bar Abba. I don't think it's the same רבי חייא, Rabbi Chiya,
but you can check that, I'm not good with that.
That would that would make it a דמיסמך Demismach because רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan and ריש לקיש Reish Lakish were later, right?
Later, right. Although they were right in the same
they weren't so later after רבי חייא, Rabbi Chiya, they were I
think there was overlap. Anyway, okay. Okay. בת חמוה דרב פפא, Bat
chamueh de'Rav Pappa, now,
the the daughter of the mother-in-law of רב פפא, Rav Pappa, which
presumably means his wife's sister, okay. Daughter of the mother-in-law? Father-in-law? חמוה.
Chamueh.
Chamueh, yeah, daughter of חמוסה. Chamoseh.
Thank you. Okay,
the daughter of the father-in-law of רב פפא. Rav Pappa. Okay, it
probably means that it was like his wife's sister, but anyway some
relative. Okay, so obviously he was interested in protecting her interest. נפלה
לפני יבם, Nafla lifnei yavam, had fell in front of the brother-in-law,
שאינו הגון לה, She'eino hagun lah, that was inappropriate for her, that
should not be doing יבום. Yibum. אתא לקמיה דאביי, Asa lekamei de'Abaye,
so he came to אביי, Abaye, and he still wanted to do
יבום, Yibum, but you know רב פפא Rav Pappa thought that was
not the right thing to be done here and רב פפא Rav
Pappa wanted to protect his his whatever
sister-in-law, whoever she was. So אתא לקמיה דאביי. Asa lekamei de'Abaye. אמר
ליה, Amar lei, so אביי Abaye said to the brother-in-law,
חלוץ לה בתחת הקונסא. Chalotz lah betachat hakonsa. So אביי Abaye tried
that trick. Do חליצה Chalitza and through that you'll be married to
her. Of course as we know that's not going to be a
good חליצה Chalitza and it'll require another thing and it's getting into
some tricky territory. So בתחת הקונסא. Betachat hakonsa. אמר ליה רב פפא,
Amar lei Rav Pappa, so רב פפא Rav Pappa said to אביי,
Abaye, לא סבר ליה מר להא דאמר רבי יוחנן? Lo savar lei
mar leha de'amar Rabbi Yochanan? Don't you hold what רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan says,
that that's not going to affect be effective as creating a חליצה?
Chalitza? אלא היכי אימא
ליה? Ella heichi eima lei? So אביי Abaye said to רב פפא,
Rav Pappa, so what should I say to him? אמר ליה, Amar
lei, say to him, חלוץ לה על מנת שתתן לך מאתיים זוז.
Chalotz lah al menas she'titen lach masayim zuz. Do agree to do
חליצה Chalitza and she'll give you two hundred זוז, zuz, which we
know will work, and you won't have to pay and the money
won't be and even without the money it'll work. לבתר דחלץ לה,
Lebasar dechalatz lah, so he did חליצה Chalitza with her, אמר ליה
אמר לה, Amar lei amar lah, so now אביי Abaye said to
the woman, זיל Zil give him the 200 זוז, zuz, not because
he necessarily thought that the חליצה chalitzah would not be good if
she didn't pay up, but you know דווקא davka because you promised,
you promised to give him 200 זוז, zuz, so even if now
the חליצה chalitzah will work either way, you should give him what
you promised. So אמר ליה, amar lei, so so רב
פפא Rav Papa said to אביי, Abaye, משטה אני בך עבד לי.
meshata ni bach avadlei. No,
she just could say I was tricking him now, meaning and therefore
forget that the חליצה chalitzah was good regardless, which we've already established,
but that also frees her from just sort of making a promise
to give money. You know, if you commit to somebody to give
money for doing something for you. Now, רש״י Rashi says, if I
say to you I'm going to give you $200 on your birthday,
that doesn't obligate me. But if I say I'm going to give
you $200 for mowing the lawn, it does obligate me. That's called
שכירות. sechirus. That's called hiring somebody. So if she said I'm going
to give you $200 for, 200 זוז zuz is a lot more,
$2,000, $20,000, for doing חליצה, chalitzah,
it might be the חליצה chalitzah is good regardless, but why don't
you have to pay him his fee? Right? This is a fee
you agreed upon. So not in דיני אבן העזר, dinei Even HaEzer,
not in דיני dinei her personal legal status, but in דיני חושן
משפט, dinei Choshen Mishpat, just in terms of like legal, you know,
in terms of civil law, you should have to pay, she should
have to pay him the money she contracted. So רב פפא Rav
Papa said no, there's conditions where you could say that even in
terms of חושן משפט, Choshen Mishpat, even in terms of monetary obligation,
you could claim I was only kidding. When are you allowed to
make the claim I was only kidding? So let's take a look.
עבד לי, avad lei, that's what she did to him, an I
was only kidding trick. Now, מי לא תניא, mi lo tanya, here's
how we see that you can make that claim. We talk in
the ברייתא: braita: הרי שהיה בורח מבית האסורין, harey she-haya bore'ach mibeit
ha'asurin, somebody was running away from prison, and obviously this is like
the Roman prison where he was unjustly imprisoned. והיה מעבר לפניו, v-haya
ma'avar lefanav, and there was a river crossing in front of him,
ואמר ליה, v-amar lei, and there was a like a raft, and
he said to the raftsman or the boatman, he said to him,
ואמר ליה, v-amar lei, טול דינר והעבירני, tol dinar v-haviani,
take this דינר, dinar, which is a lot of money, take $100
and help me cross the river. And then he does. אינו אלא
שכרו. eino ela secharo. He only has to pay him the going
rate, which was I don't know, a dollar, not $100. Because
why? Because אמר ליה משטה אני בך. amar lei meshata ni bach.
I was kidding you. Meaning obviously, now he probably wasn't kidding, but
the point is is that it's sort of like highway robbery, you
know, if you hike up your rates to take advantage of somebody
in a dire circumstance, then that person isn't obligated to pay you
more than what the real rate is, not the way you took
advantage of him. And then you can make the legal claim of
משטה אני בך. meshata ni bach. So here we're saying, you know
what, even in terms of חושן משפט, Choshen Mishpat, she doesn't have
to give him the money because normally חליצה chalitzah is not an
act that's paid for. חליצה chalitzah is supposed to be done as
a מצוה. mitzvah. It's supposed to be done for free. So any
claim that she would pay him money is not a legally binding
claim. Okay. So ואמר ליה, v-amar lei, so אינו אלא שכרו. eino
ela secharo.
אלמא אמר ליה משטה אני בך. alma amar lei meshata ni bach.
You see that he can say in that case I was kidding
you. הכא נמי משטה אני בך. hacha nami meshata ni bach. Okay,
so number one, we've established that the חליצה chalitzah will work even
without paying the money because you cannot stipulate חליצה. chalitzah. Number two,
how about the legal obligation to pay the money because you agreed
on a fee? Isn't this just like a fee? And the answer
is no. You cannot be, that type of an agreement you're not
bound by because that is a taking advantage of somebody in a
circumstance and that's not really what the fee for the services is.
So therefore not bound to pay the money. So אמר ליה, amar
lei, so אביי Abaye was somehow frustrated by all of this. Not
exactly clear why because אביי Abaye and רב פפא Rav Papa want
the same thing out of the circumstance, but maybe אביי Abaye didn't
realize that there wasn't even going to be the payment of money
or whatever. Anyway, he said to רב פפא, Rav Papa, אבוך הי,
avocha hey, where's your father? אמר ליה במתא, amar lei be-masa, he's
in the city. אמך הי, imach hey, where's your mother? אמר ליה
במתא, amar lei be-masa, in the city. So יהבו עיניה ושכיבן. yahavu
einei v-shichvan. So אביי Abaye gave them the evil eye and they
died. So like yesterday we had children dying, now we have parents
dying. You know, anyway, I really don't understand this I must say
because like what did he do that was so wrong? I mean
אביי Abaye was also going to trick him, going to trick the
sister-in-law. He was going to say do this and you'll be married
to her. רב פפא Rav Papa just had a better trick. So
it's not at all clear to me what this is about. I
don't know if your footnotes make any suggestions about why אביי Abaye
was so upset. What?
To make up a story to explain it?
I didn't
make it up, they give an explanation from הרב יעב״ץ. ha-Rav Yavetz.
Oh yeah?
Yeah, it says
אביי Abaye did not cast his gaze upon רב פפא's Rav Papa
parents for the purpose of exacting punishment from them, for indeed neither
they nor רב פפא Rav Papa was deserving of punishment. Rather, by
contemplating רב פפא's Rav Papa good fortune in having the support of
his nearby parents, אביי Abaye inadvertently caused God to examine their deeds.
Alright, fine. And undeservingly passed away. Got it. That, okay, wonderful. So
it was not so helpful. Anyway, it's a little תוספות Tosafos that's
interesting in terms of the legal issues here about... about agreeing to
pay for something when you're being taken advantage of. אין לו שכרו.
En lo s'charo. תוספות Tosafot says: היינו דוקא כגון הכא שהשיב דבר
גדול במקום שאין לוקחין על דבר מועט Hainu davka kagon hacha sheheshiv
davar gadol bemakom sheein lokchin al davar muat where somebody's asking for
an extravagant fee where the standard is much of a lesser fee.
Now, of course, if you're paying somebody to sneak you across a
river because the prison guards are after him and part of what
you're paying him for is because he's actually risking risking his life,
you know, then by helping you do that, that's a different story.
The point wasn't that, the point was was that this guy's just
taking advantage of this person in dire circumstances, but presumably it's coming
at no greater risk or cost to himself. But תוספות Tosafot says:
וכן ההיא דגוזר בבתרא גבי הולך והבא כרוב דרוס בנשכים וכולי דאין
לו אלא שכרו.
veshein haridugozar batra gabei
halach vaavi keruv d'rush benoshkin vechulei deein lo ela s'charo. אבל היכא
דלוקחין דבר גדול, Aval heicha delokchin davar gadol, but if they normally
is a big fee, התם אינו יכול לומר משטה אני בך, hacha
ein yachol lomar meshateh ani bach,
then you can't say that I was kidding, meaning the claim is
only when you're being when the person was being taken advantage of,
okay. The claim was not in these circumstances where was where there
actually was a fee to be paid or we could say where
the by the person agreeing in these circumstances he actually is, you
know, taking a serious risk or cost. Okay, back to the גמרא.
Gemara. תנו רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan: חליצה מוטעית כשרה, Chalitza mutet keshera, a
tricked חליצה chalitza's כשרה, kasher, which we've established. גט מוטעה פסול, Get
mutet pasul, a tricked גט get is פסול pasul because as we've
as we said, if a trick means you promised to do it
for payment and then the payment isn't made, well that's normally a
condition. And if the condition isn't met, the גט get is no
good, right. We explained why חליצה chalitza was different, it's not given
over to agency, so it cannot be given over to condition, but
at least in the case of גט, get, that's a normal type
of a thing which is given for agency and which you can
stipulate. So if there was a stipulation made and it wasn't satisfied,
the גט get is no good, which of course gets us to
the what do you call, which of course gets us to the
nu,
the whole issue about extortion and so on. חליצה מעושית פסולה, Chalitza
muafit pesula,
a forced חליצה, chalitza, meaning nobody's being tricked, בית דין beit din
is just saying, you know, do the חליצה chalitza or we're going
to beat you up, it's invalid. גט מעושה כשר Get meuasa kasher
is כשר. kasher. Okay, if the בית דין, beit din, if a,
right, the whole problem nowadays is when you try things like New
York state גט get law etc, you say it's being forced by
the by the secular authorities. But if the if the halachic authorities
are forcing a גט, get, then it's considered legitimate. We'll learn about
that when we learn גיטין. Gittin. So the גמרא Gemara says, גט
מעושה כשר. get meuasa kasher. Now what's the difference about being forced?
Why is חליצה chalitza no good and גט get good? So that's
what the גמרא Gemara asks.
היכי דמי, Heichi dami, what's the case? אי דאמר רוצה אני, Ee
deamar rotzeh ani, if the person is saying after being forced by
the בית דין, beit din, fine, I'm doing it willingly now that
you're twisting my arm, I'm doing it
willingly. So אפילו חליצה נמי, afillu chalitza nami, then even חליצה chalitza
should be כשר. kasher. Even though we forced you, now you're agreeing
to do it willingly. ואי לא אמר רוצה אני, Vee lo amar
rotzeh ani, if he did not say I want to do it
willingly, אפילו גט נמי לא, afillu get nami lo, so even a
גט get wouldn't be good. Meaning the way forcing a גט get
works is, you beat the guy up and then he says I
agree. Okay, so
and when we learn גיטין Gittin we'll learn more why that is
legally why that's legally valid, but the point is, but if that
is legally valid by a גט get it should be legally it's
legally valid by anything. What we're saying is that the beating up
before doesn't matter, what matters now is the I agree, so there's
nothing special about גט get that should be true by everything. Okay.
So the גמרא Gemara says you're right, הכי קאמר, hacha kaamar, this
is how it has to be read. חליצה מוטעית לעולם כשרה וגט
מוטעה לעולם פסול, Chalitza mutet leolam keshera veget mutet leolam pasul, a
tricked חליצה chalitza is always כשרה, kasher, a tricked גט get is
always פסול. pasul. Now, חליצה מעושית וגט מעושה, chalitza muafit veget meuasa,
a forced חליצה chalitza and a forced גט, get, זימנין כשר וזימנין
פסול, zimnin kasher vezimnin pasul, sometimes כשר kasher sometimes פסול. pasul. הא
דאמר רוצה אני הא דלא אמר רוצה אני, Ha deamar rotzeh ani
ha delo amar rotzeh ani, and the difference is whether in the
end he says I'm doing it willingly or not. So against the
simple read of the ברייתא Baraita saying there really is a big
difference between a there's no difference between גט get and חליצה chalitza
when it comes to being compelled. And now the גמרא's Gemara going
to look at that. דתניא, Detanya, we learned in a ברייתא: Baraita:
יקריב אותו, Yakriv oto, this is about a person bringing the קרבן.
korban. He shall offer it. מלמד שכופין אותו, Melamed shekofin oto, that
you force him if a person has an obligation to bring a
קרבן korban and he's refusing to do it, בית דין beit din
will force him to fulfill his obligation. יכול על כרחו, Yachol al
korcho, maybe even against his will? תלמוד לומר לרצונו, Talmud lomar lirtzono,
he should do it with his will. יקריב אותו, Yakriv oto, he
should be made forced to bring it willingly. So how do you
force somebody willingly? הא כיצד? Ha keitzad? כופין אותו עד שיאמר רוצה
אני. Kofin oto ad sheyomar rotzeh ani. You beat him up till
he says he wants to do it. וכן אתה מוצא בגיטי נשים,
vechen ata motze begittei nashim, similar you find by a גט. get.
כופין אותו עד שיאמר רוצה אני. Kofin oto ad sheyomar rotzeh ani.
You force him till he says I want to do it. And
that's the same true that's true by קרבן korban and גט, get,
it's true by חליצה. chalitza. So just to give you a little
a tiny little perspective on this, you know, the גמרא Gemara says
for example that if somebody had a gun held to his head
and agreed to sell something or buy something, that it also would
be binding, which is surprising right? You would think that that would
be a forced sale no good. But the גמרא's Gemara logic it
uses is that anytime this you know when a non-commercial
society it says well anytime you sell something you're doing it because
you're forced, because you're forced by dire circumstances. If you're selling off
your home or your car or your furniture, right? It's because you
know your poverty, your dire circumstances are forcing you. And at the
end of the day it doesn't matter what motivated you, it matters
that right now you want to do it. And the difference between
like desire and motivation is basically the difference. So the גמרא Gemara
says the same is true by כופין kofin if somebody held a
gun to your head. You might not- you know, your motivation was
external. Okay, the same way poverty was a motivation, the gun to
your head is external. But right now, whatever your motivation, whatever the
source of your motivation was, you actually do want to sell it
because you don't want to get your head blown off, right? So
you don't want to get the beast to beat you up. So
it's quite fascinating that the גמרא Gemara actually allows for the fact
that you know compelled transactions are legally binding because by distinguishing between
motivation and desire. So there's a question, is this always true? But
certainly in a good number of cases the גמרא Gemara actually allows
for that. There might be cases that are different, certain contract- are
contracts the same as sales and so on, but anyway it's important
to be aware of this. Yes.
I don't think this is discussed in the משנה, Mishnah, but רמב״ם
Rambam פוסק paskens that anyone who doesn't contribute the proper assessment to
the communal charity fund, we כופין kofin him. Ah, that is true.
Right,
so why is that relevant?
Well, it's another example of a- I mean he can't say I
didn't really want to do that and get the money back.
Ah well yeah, but that's different because because that's seen as a-
as a מצוה mitzvah and we're trying to like just compel you
to do a מצוה mitzvah like we compel you to take לולב
lulav or something.
Okay, that's more like- that's more like קרבן.
korban. Okay.
There maybe in prison as opposed to a physical act of coercion?
Yeah, that's even easier you know, I mean that's what they do
in Israel now. Okay. And then you know it means now also
that gets to a whole discussion that maybe withholding of privileges is
not the same as actual you know, whatever, you know,
imposing punishments. So or you know, beating somebody else. So that's why
like, you know, like you can take away somebody's driver's license and
this and that and the other thing because you're not just giving,
you're like withholding privileges. So to what degree is putting somebody in
prison just withholding the privilege of freedom you know, as opposed to-
actually what's the line between withholding a privilege and actually imposing a
penalty? But that's also relevant for this. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
says like this. תניא נמי הכי בגיטין ובדד. Tanya nami hachi beGittin
ubedid. Okay. רב אמר רבא אמר רב סחורה אמר רב הונא. Rav
amar Rava amar Rav Sechora amar Rav Huna. חולצין אף על פי
שאין מכירין. Choltzin af al pi she-ein makirin.
You can do a בית דין Beit Din can agree to do
a חליצה chalitzah ceremony even though they don't know who the guy
is. וממאנין אף על פי שאין מכירין. Umema'anin af al pi she-ein
makirin. And they could agree to do a מיאון mi'un ceremony even
though they don't know who the guy is. לפיכך אין כותבין גט
חליצה אלא אם כן מכירין. Lefikach ein kotvin get chalitzah ella im
ken makirin.
Since the בית דין Beit Din will do it without knowing who
the guy is, the witnesses can't write the document that oh, we
saw so-and-so do a you know, this woman went and did a
חליצה chalitzah with this guy in בית דין Beit Din because then
the because
if they don't know who the guy is, because because the בית
דין Beit Din may you know might not have realized, might not
have known for certain that the guy was her brother-in-law. You know
it's not like people could just come up with two you know
two you know pieces of picture ID. So a woman comes with
a man in front of בית דין, Beit Din, this is my
brother-in-law, they go through the act, and of course the woman may
have hired this guy off the street so that to trick the
בית דין Beit Din into thinking that it's the brother-in-law, right? So
the more reasonable situation would be to say that the בית דין
Beit Din should refuse to do it until they have evidence that
this is the right guy. The first position is a little bit
of- strange. The בית דין Beit Din can go ahead and do
it, you know maybe the woman won't be able to get a
בית דין Beit Din later or whatever, maybe she's just doing it
so that she'll know that she's doing the right thing and she
doesn't need any proof from the court, but she wants to be
free. So the בית דין Beit Din can go ahead and do
it, but you cannot give her any document of evidence for that
unless because you know because you might not know who the guy
is. So because because the guy might not be the right guy.
So since the בית דין Beit Din does it without knowing, then
they can't provide her with the document. So therefore, so where were
we? לפיכך אין כותבין גט חליצה אלא אם כן מכירין ואין כותבין
גט מיאון אלא אם כן מכירין. Lefikach ein kotvin get chalitzah ella
im ken makirin ve-ein kotvin get mi'un ella im ken makirin. So
if the witnesses cannot write the document just by the virtue of
the fact that the בית דין Beit Din did the ceremony. If
the witness- to write the document the witnesses would have to know
who the guy was, okay? דחיישינן לבית דין טועה, Dechayshinan le-Beit Din
to'eh,
because we're concerned that a future בית דין Beit Din might make
a mistake, see the document, not realize that the witnesses didn't know
the guy. So therefore before giving any document we're going to make
sure that the witnesses know the guy because the בית דין Beit
Din doesn't necessarily know the guy. ורבא דידיה אמר, VeRava didei amar,
but Rava on his own says, אין חולצין אלא אם כן מכירין
ואין ממאנין אלא אם כן מכירין, ein choltzin ella im ken makirin
ve-ein mema'anin ella im ken makirin, which makes total sense. You- you
refuse to do the ceremony unless you know who the parties are.
ולפיכך, Ulefikach, and since the בית דין Beit Din refuses to do
the ceremony unless they know who the parties are, the witnesses are
כותבין גט חליצה אף על פי שאין מכירין. kotvin get chalitzah af
al pi she-ein makirin. They can write the document, the proof that
this happened because they don't have to know the guy because the
בית דין beis din wouldn't have done it without the בית דין
beis din knowing who the guy was, so they can go ahead
and write the document. ולא חיישינן לבי דינא בתרא, V'lo chayshinan l'bei
dina batra, we're not afraid that some later בית דין beis din
will make a mistake as a result of this document because now
the document is totally fine because the first בית דין beis din
knew what they were doing and make sure they did it with
the right person. Okay, let's look at the next משנה. mishna. There's
different ways to read that גמרא, Gemara, but that was basically רש"י's
Rashi's way. Let's go ahead and look at the next משנה. mishna.
Okay, we will finish this פרק perek today. It's basically just a
משנה mishna and an easy גמרא Gemara on it. מצות חליצה, Mitzvas
chalitzah, finally at the end of the פרק, perek, we actually go
through the steps by step. מצות חליצה בא הוא ויבמתו
לבית דין,
Mitzvas chalitzah ba
hu viyvimto l'beis din, he and the sister-in-law came to the בית
דין. beis din. והן משיאין לו עצה ההוגנת לו, V'hen masi'in lo
eitzah ha'hogenes lo, they give him proper advice that's fitting for him,
meaning based on whether he should do חליצה chalitzah or should do
ייבום. yibum. שנאמר וקראו לו זקני עירו ודברו אליו She'ne'emar v'karu lo
ziknei iro v'dibru eilav or ודברו אליו, v'dibru eilav, I think it's
ודברו אליו. v'dibru eilav.
So they call him and they speak to him, so meaning first
they advise him which of the two to do, חליצה chalitzah or
ייבום. yibum. Now if they're deciding that they're going to do חליצה,
chalitzah, היא אומרת מאן יבמי להקים לאחיו שם בישראל לא אבה יבמי,
Hi omeres me'ein yivmi l'hakim l'achiv shem b'Yisrael lo avah yivmi, my
brother-in-law does not want to establish his brother's name. לא אבה יבמי,
Lo avah yivmi, he does not want to do the ייבום yibum
act. והוא אומר, V'hu omer, and then he says לא חפצתי לקחתה.
Lo chafatzti l'kach-tah. Right,
everybody reads their script, right? He says I don't want to take
her. And we said before that the קריאה kriyah is not מעכב,
me'akev, but this is how you do the קריאה. kriyah. ובלשון הקודש
היו אומרים, U'vilshon hakodesh hayu omerim, and they say it in Hebrew.
And the משנה mishna in סוטה Sotah says this is one of
the, you know, discusses which things have to be in the original
Hebrew and which can be in translation. ובלשון הקודש היו אומרים. U'vilshon
hakodesh hayu omerim. ונגשה יבמתו אליו לעיני הזקנים. V'nigshah yivimto eilav l'einei
hazkenim.
So the sister-in-law got close to him in the presence of the
elders, of the בית דין. beis din. וחלצה נעלו מעל רגלו וירקה
בפניו. V'chaltzah na'alo mei'al raglo v'yarkah b'fanav. So basically just quoting the
פסוקים psukim to tell you what you do
next. הרוק, Harok, she spits. Now the משנה mishna sticks in: רוק
הנראה לדיינים, Rok hanireh l'dayanim, it has to be visible spit. And
we discussed before whether the spitting is מעכב. me'akev. וענתה ואמרה ככה
יעשה לאיש אשר לא יבנה את בית אחיו, V'ansah v'amrah kachah yei'aseh
l'ish asher lo yivneh es beis achiv,
so that's her next recital of the verse. עד כאן היו מקרין,
Ad kan hayu makrin, until this point would they recite, you know,
sort of have her recite after them. They would say and then
they would recite afterwards, she would recite after them. וכשהקריא רבי הורקנס
תחת האלה בכפר עיטם, U'cheshehikri Rebbi Horkanus tachas ha'elah b'Kfar Eitam,
when רבי הורקנס Rebbi Horkanus read under the אלה elah in כפר
עיטם, Kfar Eitam, וגמר כל הפרשה, v'gamar kol haparshah,
he finished the whole פרשה, parshah, meaning he didn't just have her
say ככה יעשה לאיש אשר לא יבנה את בית אחיו, kachah yei'aseh
l'ish asher lo yivneh es beis achiv, he said what the end
of the פסוק pasuk is, ונקרא שמו בישראל בית חלוץ הנעל. V'nikra
shemo b'Yisrael beis chalutz hana'al. Right, that
that's part of, meaning who is talking at that stage? Is she
saying "his name will be called the house of the removed shoe"
or is the narrator of the פסוק pasuk saying, right? Is it
that she shall say "this will be done" and and and she
says ונקרא שמו בישראל v'nikra shemo b'Yisrael or is the verse saying
"his name will be called"? So when he did it, he had
her say the end of the verse, ונקרא שמו בישראל בית חלוץ
הנעל. V'nikra shemo b'Yisrael beis chalutz hana'al. And after he did that,
הוחזקו להיות קוראין כל הפרשה, Huhuzku lihyos korin kol haparshah, everybody then
got into the practice of having her say the entire till the
entire end of the פסוק, pasuk, ונקרא שמו בישראל בית חלוץ הנעל.
V'nikra shemo b'Yisrael beis chalutz hana'al. Okay, מצוה בדיינים. Mitzvah b'dayanim.
Now the מצוה mitzvah of declaring that he is the house of
the withdrawn shoe is on the judges. ולא מצוה בתלמידים, V'lo mitzvah
b'talmidim, not in the students. Okay, it's the actual judges, not there
like at, you know, not there, whatever, you know, not the students
of the judges. רבי יהודה אומר מצוה על כל העומדים שם, Rebbi
Yehuda omer mitzvah al kol ha'omdim sham, no, it's not just the
judges and it's not just the students, everybody present in the ceremony
should take, because it's בישראל b'Yisrael sham, לומר חלוץ הנעל, lomar chalutz
hana'al, removed shoe.
Which makes sense, it says בישראל, b'Yisrael, but until now we've been
interpreting בישראל b'Yisrael as refers to the דיינים, dayanim, which has gone
into הלכה halacha about what are the criteria for the דיינים. dayanim.
Yes, Charlie.
Rabbi Hyrcanus? Would he be the Rabbi Hyrcanus who had several sons
who were mentioned in the Talmud?
I guess so. יוסי בן הורקנס?
Yose
ben Horkanus? Yeah, he'd be pretty early in that case.
Yeah, yeah, he is early. Okay, אמר יהודה. Amar Yehuda. Now a
lot of what we're about to say we've already said before. אמר
יהודה
מצות חליצה קראה וקרא. Amar Yehuda mitzvas chalitzah karah v'karah. So the
מצוה mitzvah of חליצה chalitzah is she recites and he recites. וחלצה
ורקקה, V'chaltzah v'rakakah, she removes the shoe, she does the spitting, וקראה,
v'karah, and then she recites the final verses. So that's just a
nice distilled way of saying it, right? קראה וקרא וחלצה ורקקה וקראה.
Karah v'karah v'chaltzah v'rakakah v'karah. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says מאי קא משמע לן, Mai ka mashma
lan, what are you telling us? מתניתין היא, Masnisin hi, it's our
משנה. mishna. Okay, you tell her say it's פסוקים. psukim. Anyway, so
I would think that he's not telling us a big חידוש, chiddush,
he's just giving us a nice simple way to remember. But the
גמרא Gemara says no, הא קא משמע לן, Ha ka mashma lan,
he's teaching us מצוה הכי. mitzvah hachi. That's the מצוה. mitzvah. He
says מצוה mitzvah is to do it this way. ואי אפיך לית
לן בה, V'ei afich leis lan bah,
but if you reverse some of the orders, it's not. not a
problem as we said. If the spitting comes earlier, the verses are
out of order, the verses בדיעבד bediavad aren't even מעכב. meakev. תניא
נמי הכי, Tanya Nami Hachi, we taught similarly, בין שהקדים חליצה לרקיקה
בין שהקדים רקיקה לחליצה, Bein She'hikdim Chalitzah L'rekikah Bein She'hikdim Rekikah L'chalitzah,
whether the spitting first or the חליצה chalitzah first, מה שעשה עשוי,
Mah She'asah Asuy, either way it works. אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, האי
מאן דמקרי גט חליצה, Hai Man D'makrei Get Chalitzah, the person who's
reciting the חליצה chalitzah ceremony, I say גט חליצה get chalitzah but
it doesn't mean actually the writ, it means like it's just doing
like the script might be the better word here. The person who's
just doing the reciting of the script, meaning the בית דין Beis
Din that's saying the recite after me. Okay, לא ליקרי לדידה, Lo
Likri L'didah,
when you're having her recite, don't say to her לא Lo לחודיה
L'chudeih ואבא יבמי V'aba Yabmi לחודיה. L'chudeih.
Don't say לא, Lo, say לא, Lo, לא. Lo. Now say אבא
יבמי, Aba Yabmi, אבא יבמי. Aba Yabmi. Because that actually puts the
comma in the wrong place, right? דמשמע, D'mashma, that implies אבא יבמי,
Aba Yabmi, my brother-in-law does want to. לא, Lo, no, it's not
true. אבא יבמי, Aba Yabmi, he wants to do it. Don't say
that. אלא לא אבא יבמי. Ela Lo Aba Yabmi. Say it in
one phrase, he doesn't want to do it. ולא ליקרי לדידיה, V'lo
Likri L'dideih, and when they're having him read it, don't say לא
Lo לחודיה, L'chudeih, first לא, Lo, and then חפצתי Chafatzti לחודיה, L'chudeih,
I desire.
No, it's not true. חפצתי, Chafatzti, I do want to. Don't do
that. דמשמע חפצתי, D'mashma Chafatzti,
I want to לקחתה L'kachatah to take her. אלא לא חפצתי לקחתה,
Ela Lo Chafatzti L'kachatah, I don't want to take her. ורבא אמר,
V'Rava Amar, רבא Rava says no, פסוקי מילתא היא, Pesukei Miltha He,
it's just making a pause. פסוקי מילתא לא סבירא לן, Pesukei Miltha
Lo Savira Lan, we're not bothered by that, like the context makes
it clear. Now there's another גירסא Girsa which is not he's just
making a pause, but אפסוקי מילתא, Afisukei Miltha, he's just completing his
sentence. If he says לא Lo and then he says אבא יבמי,
Aba Yabmi, that's clearly completing the sentence he began with. It's the
same point, but it makes a little bit more sense. Like he's
emphasizing, don't get worried, he's completing his sentence. Okay. ובדיקי אשכחיה רב
פפא ורב הונא בריה דרב יהושע לרב כהנא V'vadiki Ashchacheih Rav Papa
V'Rav Huna Breih D'Rav Yehoshua L'Rav Kahana דקמצטער ומקרי לה D'kamitztayer U'makrei
Lah לא אבא יבמי. Lo Aba Yabmi. He was going to pains
to make sure that he says the whole thing in one sentence,
לא אבא יבמי. Lo Aba Yabmi. Now why are you מצטער, mitztayer,
how hard is it to say this? But maybe it's somebody that's
not so literate, right? And if somebody's not so literate, it's not
maybe it's not so easy for them to remember three words, you
know, maybe even meaningless words in they're, you know, it's a language
they don't understand all at one time. It's a lot easier to
do one word at a time. So he was going to a
lot of pains to try to do the whole phrase at once.
אמר ליה, Amar Leh,
he said to him, לא סבר ליה מר להא דרבא, Lo Savar
Leh Mar L'ha D'Rava, don't you hold what רבא Rava says that
if you make pauses it's not a problem? אמר ליה, Amar Leh,
no, מודה רבא בלא אבא יבמי. Modeh Rava B'lo Aba Yabmi.
רבא Rava agrees that the verse "he does not want to יבמי"
yabmi which is being used as a verb, he does not want
to do the יבום yibum act, there you cannot make any pauses.
Now why is that different? So רש"י Rashi says because that verse
comes right in the middle, meaning it's מאן יבמי להקים שם לאחיו
בישראל Ma'ein Yabmi L'hakim Shem L'achiv B'Yisrael right, what is it, מאן
יבמי להקים שם לאחיו בישראל לא אבא יבמי. Ma'ein Yabmi L'hakim Shem
L'achiv B'Yisrael Lo Aba Yabmi. So if it doesn't,
so any if the verse starts like if she starts לא חפצתי
לקחתה, Lo Chafatzti L'kachatah, nothing preceded it. So presumably it's not לא
Lo period חפצתי לקחתה, Chafatzti L'kachatah, it's לא חפצתי לקחתה. Lo Chafatzti
L'kachatah. But here where it appears in the middle of a verse,
מאן יבמי להקים שם לאחיו בישראל, Ma'ein Yabmi L'hakim Shem L'achiv B'Yisrael,
then it could be לא, Lo, no, that's not true. אבא יבמי.
Aba Yabmi. Somehow because it's somehow there's words that precede it, the
לא Lo could more easily be seen as not connected to the
following words but a rejection of what he said before. Okay. So
if that is, so for that phrase לא אבא יבמי Lo Aba
Yabmi he was made sure to say it all as one. Okay.
אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, האי מאן דכתב גיטא דחליצתא, Hai Man D'chasav
Gitta D'chalitzta,
if somebody is writing the גט get of חליצה chalitzah and here
the גט get means the actual, you know, writ of evidence that
it occurred, האי מאן דכתב גיטא דחליצתא, Hai Man D'chasav Gitta D'chalitzta,
ליכתוב הכי, Lichtov Hachi,
have them write it this way. אקרינוהו לדידה, Akrinuhu L'didah, we recited
made her
we recited the verses for her מן מאן יבמי Min Ma'ein Yabmi
עד לא אבא יבמי, Ad Lo Aba Yabmi, from the beginning of
מאן יבמי Ma'ein Yabmi until the end of the verse, meaning dot
dot dot, say don't write out the whole verse. Say we recited
from this part to that part, from מאן יבמי Ma'ein Yabmi to
לא אבא יבמי Lo Aba Yabmi he does not desire to to
do יבום. yibum. ואקרינוהו לדידיה V'akrinuhu L'dideih and we had him recite
מן לא עד לקחתה, min lo ad lekachta. from the part of
לא Lo
until the words to take her. Now that's very bizarre, why not
just say לא חפצתי לקחתה? Lo Chafatzti L'kachatah? They go out of
your way to remove one of the three words and place it
with the word עד Ad or put in three dots. So we're
going to see it's a what he's particularly the concern is is
that you're not allowed to write biblical verses without doing שרטוט. sirtut.
שרטוט Sirtut is scoring. If you ever look at a ספר תורה,
Sefer Torah, there are lines. Actually, people are not aware, but the
שרטוט sirtut is lines above, not lines below. Right? It's not obviously
ink lines, it's like it's like, you know, it's like scratched-in lines,
but the line will look like this and then it'll be like,
you know, אבל aval and like it becomes also the upper line,
right? The top of the letters are there and then you have
like the bigger letters which go beyond above it. Anyway, that's called
שרטוט, sirtut, scoring. So so a, they didn't score these documents, and
maybe even if they did score the documents, we'll see in a
minute, you don't want to be sort of like writing out biblical
verses in a document if it's not really a ספר תורה Sefer
Torah or a מגילה. Megillah. So therefore specifically take out middle words
of the verse even if it's just one word in order not
to write a whole section of the verse. Right? And three or
four words already requires שרטוט. sirtut. Okay? So מן לא Min Lo
עד
לקחתה. Ad L'kachatah,
We had him read from the word לא lo until לקחתה. lekachta.
ואיהי בדידה ve'ihi bidida and then we had her read the verse
מן ככה ועד וחלוץ הנעל. min kacha ve'ad vachulutz hana'al. Okay?
So the beginning and the end are no more than three words.
Okay? You don't have three words all in a row. מר זוטרא
משרטט וכתב לכולה פרשה. Mar Zutra mesartet vechatav lechula parasha. So
Mar Zutra made the שרטוט sirtut and he wrote out the whole
thing. Okay, now it says לכולה פרשה lechula parasha sounds like he
might have written out the, not just the whole section that they
said, but maybe the entire פרשה. parasha. That's what it sounds like.
Anyway, מתקיף לה רב פפא בר אידי matkif lah Rav Papa bar
Idi to רב פפא בר אידי, Rav Papa bar Idi, והא לא
ניתנו לכתוב, veha lo nitnu lichtov, but you're not allowed to write
individual sections of the Torah, I mean you can write a מזוזה,
mezuzah, you can write תפילין, tefillin, you can write a ספר תורה,
Sefer Torah, but you can't write out individual sections if they're not
in the context of some type of a ספר. sefer. So the
גמרא Gemara says, והלכתא כמר זוטרא vehilchata keMar Zutra and nevertheless we
rule like Mar Zutra. Now why is that? What's this idea of
not writing it out separately? So if you look at רש"י, Rashi,
he says והא לא ניתנו לכתוב. veha lo nitnu lichtov. רש"י Rashi
says, פרשה בפני עצמה, parasha bifnei atzma, about twenty lines from the
bottom, פרשה בפני עצמה במסכת גיטין פרק הניזוקין דתני אין כותבין מגילה
לתינוק להתלמד בה. parasha bifnei atzma bemasechet Gittin perek Hanizukin detani ein
kotvin megillah letinok lehitlamed bah. You don't write like a little mini
ספר. sefer. Okay, והלכתא כמר זוטרא, vehilchata keMar Zutra, but we rule
you can write out a section with שרטוט. sirtut. דכותבין, dekotvin, you
can write it out as long as you do the שרטוט. sirtut.
ולא דמי לכותב מגילה לתינוק להתלמד. velo dami lechotev megillah letinok lehitlamed.
דהתם אדעתא דפרשה כתיב לה. dehatam ada'ata deparasha ketiv leh.
There you're writing it as sort of a little mini ספר. sefer.
דתיהוי כמיגילה קטנה וקיימא לן תורה חתומה ניתנה. detehevi kemegilla ktana vekayma
lan Torah chatuma nitna. You have to write the whole תורה Torah
if you're going to write it, you know, maybe an individual בראשית,
Bereishit, you know, שמות, Shemot,
you can write maybe a whole חומש chumash of the תורה, Torah,
or, you know, something for the מזוזה, mezuzah,
but you can't write smaller units. אבל האי שטרא הוא. aval hai
shtra hu. This is not written as a mini ספר. sefer. This
is written to inform what it was that was recited. ולא לקדושה
הוא, velo lekdusha hu, and it's not written as a ספר. sefer.
הלכך hilkach and therefore הלכתא כמר זוטרא דבמקום מצוה שרי. hilchata keMar
Zutra debemakom mitzvah shari.
If you're doing it for the purpose of this document, it's allowed.
Let's finish up the פרק. perek. Okay, fine. אמר אביי, amar Abaye,
רקקה וקלטתה הרוח, rakaka vekaltata haruach, she spat at him and the
wind blew it away. לא עשה ולא כלום, lo asa velo klum,
it doesn't count as a spitting. Now, it depends whether spitting is
needed בדיעבד, bedi'avad, but what it is, it's needed, it doesn't count
as a spitting if it didn't go in his presence, it was
blown away from the wind. מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama, what's the reason?
וירקה בפניו בעינן, veyarka befanav ba'inan, it has to be in his
presence. הלכך, hilkach, now, sometimes yes, sometimes no, where the
wind make a difference? הוא ארוך והיא גוצה, hu aroch vehi gutza,
if he's tall and she's short, קלטתה הרוח איכא בפניו, kaltata haruach
ika befanav,
then even if the wind blows it away, as soon as it
went out of her mouth, it was in his presence because he
was taller than she was, he was standing right in front of
her, right? So then that's fine. היא ארוכה והוא גוץ, hi aruka
vehu gotz, she's
tall and he's short. So it leaves her mouth, it's not yet
in his presence because it's above him, right? The spit is up
there and he's down here, right? In that case, so that's where
the problem. בעינן עד דמטי להדי אפיה. ba'inan ad demati lahadi apeih.
The spit has to get in front of his face. Not, it
doesn't hit him, it goes to the ground, but it has to
be in front of his face, right? If it's higher than him
and the wind blows it away before it gets in front of
his face, it's no good. והדר אזיל, vehadar azil, once it gets
in front of his face, then if it's blown away it's not
a problem. אמר רבא, amar Rava, אכל תומא ורקקתא, achal tuma verakakta,
if she ate garlic and spat, אכל גרגישתא ורקקתא achal gargishta verakakta
or some other thing. What's גרגישתא? gargishta? What does your English say?
Clay. Clay? Alright, whatever. Anyway, an Aramaic word for clay. Okay, fine.
Clay, it's
not, she didn't do anything. מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama, it doesn't count
as spitting. Why? וירקה מעצמה בעינן, veyarka me'atzma ba'inan, she has to
spit on her own accord, not that something else is generating the
spit. וליכא. velika. ואמר רבא, ve'amar Rava, צריכי דייני למיחזי רוקא כי
נפיק מפומה דיבמה. tzrichi dayanei lemichzi roka ki nafik mipuma diyevama.
The judges have to see the spit when it leaves the mouth
of the sister-in-law. דכתיב לעיני הזקנים וירקה, dechtiv le'einei hazekenim veyarka, to
the eyes of the elders and she shall spit. So the spit
has to be seen directly by them. The act of spitting. ונקרא
שמו בישראל בית חלוץ הנעל, venikra shemo beYisrael beit chulutz hana'al, declaring
his name the house of the removee of the shoe. מצוה בדייני
ולא בתלמידים. mitzvah bedayanei velo betalmidim. So first it says the judges
do it, that's בישראל, beYisrael, then it says everybody standing there does
it. And the פרק perek continues, concludes. תניא, tanya, we taught in
a ברייתא. braita. אמר רבי יהודה, amar Rabbi Yehuda, פעם אחת היינו
יושבים לפני רבי טרפון, pa'am achat hayinu yoshvim lifnei Rabbi Tarfon,
once we were sitting in front of Rabbi Tarfon, ובאה יבמה לחלוץ,
uvah yevama lachlotz, and the sister-in-law came to חליצה, chalitza, ואמר לנו,
ve'amar lanu, and Rabbi Tarfon said to us... Say all of you,
חלוצה נא, חלוצה נא, חלוצה נא, chalutza na, chalutza na, chalutza na,
three times, like how הכל מותר לך, kol mutar lach, הכל שרוי
לך, kol sharui lach, right, מותר לך, מותר לך, מותר לך, mutar
lach, mutar lach, mutar lach, so that's made it clear that that's
the status, and that's and that and that sort of formalizes the
end of the process. הדרן עלך מצות חליצה. Hadran alach mitzvas chalitza.
Okay. You know, this is sounding more demeaning to the man.
Yeah. The way, well, the Torah intends it to be.